Guide to the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Letters and Manuscripts
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Chauncey Brewster Tinker letters and manuscripts
1900-1963
GEN MSS 359
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.25
(4 boxes) + 1 broadside, 1 portfolio
Collection consists of correspondence, writings, and other papers by or relating to Chauncey Brewster Tinker. Correspondence contains mostly letters by Tinker, including letters to Albert S. Cook, Lansing V. Hammond, Mary Etta Knapp, E. L. McAdam, Daniel and Mary Merriman, and Mary (Mrs. George Henry) Nettleton. Writings contain holograph, typescript and printed versions of writings by Tinker and others.
Tinker, Chauncey Brewster, 1876-1963
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Source information is recorded on the folders. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile materials in the portfolio may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
Associated Materials
Chauncey Brewster Tinker Papers (GEN MSS 354), Chauncey Brewster Tinker Manuscript Collection (GEN MSS 310), and various printed books donated to the Library by Tinker, cataloged separately.
CHAUNCEY BREWSTER TINKER, 1876-1963
A full biographical statement is provided in the register for the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Papers (GEN MSS 354).
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Chauncey Brewster Tinker, acquired by the library from a variety of sources. Materials incorporated into the collection prior to July 1998 have been organized into three series. Series I, Mr. and Mrs. Gordon S. Haight Gift, contains letters from Tinker to members of the Haight and Nettleton families, and one clipping of an obituary of Tinker. Series II, Robert F. Metzdorf Gift, contains articles and other writings by Tinker and others. Series III, Materials from Other Sources, contains letters, writings and other papers by and about Tinker.
Educators; Cook, Albert S. (Albert Stanburrough), 1853-1927; Hammond, Lansing V. (Lansing Van der Heyden), 1906-; Knapp, Mary E., 1902-; McAdam, E. L. (Edward Lippincott), 1905-1969; Merriman, Daniel; Merriman, Mary; Nettleton, Mary, 1872-1964; Tinker, Chauncey Brewster, 1876-1963; Yale University -- Alumni and alumnae; Yale University -- Faculty
- Mr. and Mrs. Gordon S. Haight Gift, 1923-1963; Series I; 0.1; (.5 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Gordon S. Haight, 1983
  - LETTERS FROM CBT
    - Haight, Briny [Sabrina, the Haights' dog], 1950 May 22 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Haight, Gordon Sherman, 1923-36 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Haight, Mary Nettleton, 1929, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Nettleton, George Henry, 1930 Nov 16 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Nettleton, Mary [Mrs. George Henry], 1927-47 (Box 1, Folder 5-7)
  - ADDITIONAL MATERIALS
    - Obituary of CBT, New Haven Journal- Courier, 1963 Mar 18 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Robert F. Metzdorf Gift, 1903-1949; Series II; 0.5; (1.5 boxes)
  Gift of Robert F. Metzdorf, 1969
  - WRITINGS OF CHAUNCEY BREWSTER TINKER
    - "An Age of Enlightenment (England, 1740-90)," 3 copies, printed version, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      In 3 copies of The Age of Enlightenment: Proceedings of the Humanities Institute, sponsored jointly by the University of Toledo and The Toledo Museum of Art
    - " Astraea: A Neglected Poem of Oliver Wendell Holmes," typescript, corrected (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Authors Who 'Go Out'," clipping of printed version, The Atlantic Monthly, 2 copies, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "The Bertrams," holograph, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "Boswell's Letters to Rousseau," clipping of printed version, The Literary Review, 1922 Jun 3 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "British Poetry Under Stress of War," clipping of printed version, The Yale Review, 1920 Jul (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "Bryn Mawr," typescript, corrected (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - "The Caliph Of Books: A. E. N.," clipping of printed version, The Atlantic Monthly, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Convocation citations for Honorary Degrees, presented by CBT, clipping of printed version, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Presentation of degree to CBT by W. S. (Wilmarth Sheldon) Lewis
    - Exhibition of Eighteenth Century English Painting, in Honor of Professor Chauncey Brewster Tinker, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Printed pamphlet from the Fogg Art Museum, with prefatory note by CBT
    - "Gainsborough, An Address delivered at the Frick Gallery" typescript, corrected, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "The Gutenberg Bible as a Typeographical Monument," printed version, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      In The Yale University Library Gazette, June 1926
    - "Hogarth," typescript, corrected, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "In Praise of Nursery Lore," clipping of printed version, The Unpopular Review, 1916 Oct (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - "Introduction," for unidentified work, clipping of printed version with corrections, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - "Maeterlinck and the Stage," 2 copies of printed version, [1902?] (Box 2, Folder 24)
      One copy in The Prologue, A Pamphlet, one copy clipped
    - "Man the Insurgent," clipping of printed version, The Yale Review, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 25)
      With: One negative photocopy
    - "Man's Natural State," clipping of printed version, The Saturday Review of Literature, 1928 Aug 25 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - "The Modern Essay," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - "Newman's Secession, 1845," clipping of printed version, Holy Cross Magazine, 1945 Oct (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - "Newton's Trollope Society," reprinted from The Trollopian, 2 copies, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - "The Pilot of Life," printed version, 3 copies, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - "The Poet, The Bramble, and Reconstruction," clipping of printed version, The Atlantic Monthly, 1919 Nov (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - "The Poetry of Christina Rossetti," clipping of printed version, American Church Monthly, 1918 Jun (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - "Pre-Raphaelites and Labor," clipping of printed version, Literary Review, 1922 Jul 29 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - "Presentation of the Gold Medal of the American Academy of Arts and Letters to Bruce Rogers," printed version, 1948 May 21 (Box 2, Folder 34)
      Includes: Acceptance by Mr. Rogers
    - "The Quality of Mercy," address to the graduating class, School of Nursing of the Presbyterian Hospital, New York City, printed version, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - "Rasselas in the New World," clipping of printed version, The Yale Review, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - "Reflections of a Curator," printed version, The Yale University Library Gazette, 1948 Jul (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - "Religion After the War," printed version, 1944 Jan (Box 2, Folder 38)
      One copy in The Ripon Alumnus, one copy clipped
    - "Restudying Life and Work of Matthew Arnold," clipping of printed version, Boston Evening Transcript Book Review, 1939 Feb 25 (Box 2, Folder 39)
      Review of Matthew Arnold by Lionel Trilling
    - "Shelley's 'I Arise from Dreams of Thee'," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - "The Significance to Yale of the Gift of the Gutenberg Bible," clipping of printed version, The Yale University Library Gazette, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - "The Text of Trollope's Phineas Redux ", printed version, [1942] (Box 2, Folder 42)
      Includes response from R. W. Chapman
    - "The University Library: An Address on Alumni University Day," printed version, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 43)
      CBT's well-known address which emphasizes the importance of the University Library and encourages support by its patrons
    - "Walter Crane," by "C. T. P. and C. B. T.," clipping of printed version, Brooklyn Art Museum Quarterly, 1924 Jan (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Unidentified article fragment on A. E. (Alfred Edward) Housman, clipping of printed version, The Yale Review, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Unidentified typescript fragment on Dante Alighieri and Percy Bysshe Shelley (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Untitled article on John Milton, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Untitled article on Alfred, Lord Tennyson, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Untitled typescript fragments, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - WRITINGS OF OTHERS
    - Burrell, Joe. "Trollope's Lost Children," letter to the editor, unidentified newspaper, 1946 Feb 9 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Chapman, R. W. (Robert William). "The Text of Trollope's Novels," reprinted by Oxford University Press from The Review of English Studies, 1941 Apr (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Chapman, R. W. (Robert William). "The Text of Trollope's Phineas Redux ", reprinted by Oxford University Press from The Review of English Studies, 1941 Apr (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Ratchford, Fannie Elizabeth. "Idylls of the Hearth: Wise's Forgery of Enoch Arden Southwest Review, Spring 1941 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Watkins, W. B. C. (Walter Barker Critz). "An Esthetic Ignored," clipping of printed version, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 54)
      Review of Trollope: A Commentary by Michael Sadleir
    - Unidentified. "Anthony Trollope," clipping of printed version, The Times Literary Supplement, 1927 Jan 20 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Unidentified. "For the Trollopians," clipping of printed version, The Church Times, 1927 Jan 28 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Unidentified. "The True Tale of Shelley's 'Emily'," clipping of printed version, The Times Literary Supplement, 1937 Jan 23 (Box 2, Folder 57)
      Review of Vita di una donna by Enrica Viviani Della Robbia
  - ADDITIONAL MATERIALS
    - "Barrie on Trollope. Letters ed. by V. Meynell," typescript copies of quotes, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - "Checklist for A. Trollope," holograph notes and list in the hand of CBT (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Convocation program, Yale University, 1946 Oct (Box 2, Folder 60)
      "Presentation of Candidates for Honorary Degrees by the Public Orator, Chauncey Brewster Tinker"
    - Holograph notes on Percy Bysshe Shelley and Dante Alighieri, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Holograph notes on Anthony Trollope, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Holograph notes in an unidentified hand (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Note in CBT's hand, "Papers relating to the text of Trollope, correspondence with R. W. Chapman, etc." (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Notebook of holograph notes on Anthony Trollope in the hand of CBT, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Notes in CBT's hand, 4 p., 1903-05 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Robbins, Frank E. "A Trollopian Chronology," printed item, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Typescript copy of entry in Dorothy Wordsworth's Grasmere journal, and copy in CBT's hand of 2 poems (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - The Yale University Library Gazette, 1935 Jul (Box 2, Folder 69)
      Includes: Article about the Ionides Collection of Greek Classics, gift to the Library by CBT
- Materials from Other Sources, 1900-1956; Series III; 0.6; (2 boxes)
  Acquired by gift or purchase from various sources, as indicated on individual folders
  - LETTERS FROM CBT
    - Barber, John E., 1940-48 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Boyd, Janice, 1907-49, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 71)
      Acc #: 19670227-b
    - Buck, Philo Melvin, 1919 Apr 25 (Box 3, Folder 72)
      Acc #: 19760302-a
    - Canby, Henry Seidel, 1936 Sep 4 (Box 3, Folder 73)
      Acc #: 19720707-a
    - Converse, Allan D., Jr., 1936 Apr 15 (Box 3, Folder 74)
      Acc #: 19770209-a
    - Cook, Albert S., 1910-24 (Box 3, Folder 75-76)
      Includes: One letter from Cook
      Acc #: 19680701-n
    - Cournos, John, 1941 Mar 27 (Box 3, Folder 77)
      Includes: Photocopy of clipping of article by Cournos
    - Dunham, Albert M., 1914 Oct 24 (Box 3, Folder 78)
      Acc #: 19791105-a
    - Fletcher, Edward G.
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Lansing V. Hammond, Box 3, folder 79
    - Hammond, Lansing V., 1930-56 (Box 3, Folder 79-85)
      Includes: TLS to CBT from Edward G. Fletcher, Nov. 2, 1938
      Includes: ALS from Catherine T. Patterson, July 1, 1956
      Acc #: 19580609-a
    - Hogan, Charles Beecher, 1945 Jun 5 (Box 3, Folder 86)
      Acc #: 19701204-u
    - Ingalls, Gertrude, 1932 Aug 30 (Box 3, Folder 87)
      Drafts of letter
    - Keller, Deane, 1936 Mar (Box 3, Folder 88)
      See also: "Sitter to Painter," Box 4, folder 116
    - Keogh, Andrew, 1932-33 (Box 3, Folder 89)
      Includes: Letter from Keogh to CBT
    - Knapp, Mary Etta, 1945-56, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 90-95)
      Acc #: 19680806-c
    - Lewis, Robert M., 1955 Feb 14 (Box 3, Folder 96)
      Acc #: 19630402-b
    - Loveman, Amy, 1930 Jul 20 (Box 3, Folder 97)
    - McAdam, E. L. (Edward Lippincot), 1936-55, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 98-101)
      Includes: TLS from McAdam to CBT
      See also: "Phi Beta Kappa..." Box 4, folder 122
      Acc #: 19701215-b
    - Merriman, Daniel Merriman, Mary, 1948-56 (Box 3, Folder 102-103)
      Acc #: 19691218-f
    - Patterson, Catherine T.
      Sister of CBT
      See: Lansing V. Hammond, Box 3, folder 85
    - Smith, F. C., 1906 Aug 25 (Box 4, Folder 104)
    - Taylor, Henry C., 1931 Apr 1 (Box 4, Folder 105)
      Acc #: 19800915-b
    - Tinker, Mrs. A. P. (Martha Jane White Tinker, mother), 1919 (Box 4, Folder 106)
    - Troxell, Gilbert McCoy, 1927, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 107)
      Letter of July 9, 1927 is Acc #: 19741009-a
    - Wagner, Charles, 1900-54, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 108-111)
      Acc #: 19651215-c
    - Wolf, Lydia Hubbard, 1940-48 (Box 4, Folder 112-113)
      Acc #: 19840215-b
    - "Dear Miss Traaer[?]", 1922 Mar 1 (Box 4, Folder 114)
  - WRITINGS
    - "Samson Agonistes," notes in CBT's hand, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 115)
      With envelope, and overdue book notice to Mark Dronin[?] from the Saranac Lake (N. Y.) Free Library, 1940
      Acc #: 951102-n
    - "Samson Agonistes," proofs, n.d.
    - "Sitter to Painter," holograph poem, with typescript, 1936 Jun (Box 4, Folder 116)
      Includes: 2 ALS from Deane Keller to Herman W. Liebert and Marjorie Wynne regarding the poem, July 1965
      Acc #: 19650723-az
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Certificate of the Yale Medal, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 117)
      Acc #: 19640417-a
    - Diploma for the honorary degree to CBT from Yale University, 1946 Jun (Box 4, Folder 118)
    - National Institute of Arts and Letters (U.S.), membership certificate, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 119)
    - Obituary of CBT, clipping from the Baltimore Sun, 1963 Mar 18 (Box 4, Folder 120)
    - Obituary of CBT, clipping from Time, 1963 Mar 29 (Box 4, Folder 121)
    - "Phi Beta Kappa, One Hundred and Sixty- eighth Anniversary of the Alpha of Virginia," College of William and Mary, printed program, 1944 Dec 5 (Box 4, Folder 122)
      Includes: ALS on back from CBT to E. L. (Edward Lippincot) McAdam, December 8, 1944
    - Photograph of Henry Davenport's portrait of CBT, made for the Yale Alumni Weekly, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 123)
      Acc #: 19741009-a
    - Tuttle, Henry Emerson. Notes taken in CBT's class, "The Age of Johnson", 1919 (Box 4, Folder 124)
      Includes: TLS from Tuttle to Emily H. Hall
      Acc #: 19720315-a
- Oversize
  (1 broadside)
  - "Samson Agonistes," proofs (in Series III), n.d. (Box bsd, folder 125)
- Restricted Fragile
  (1 portfolio)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 8 (Box port, Folder 126)
  - Box 1, folder 13 (Box port, Folder 127)
  - Box 2, folder 26 (Box port, Folder 128)
  - Box 2, folder 33 (Box port, Folder 129)
  - Box 2, folder 39 (Box port, Folder 130)
  - Box 2, folder 50 (Box port, Folder 131)
  - Box 2, folder 54 (Box port, Folder 132)
  - Box 2, folder 55 (Box port, Folder 133)
  - Box 2, folder 56 (Box port, Folder 134)
  - Box 2, folder 57 (Box port, Folder 135)